Guide to the Melchior Palyi Papers 1915-1970
University of Chicago Library
Palyi, Melchior. Papers
1915-1970
13 linear feet (26 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Melchior Palyi, economist and professor. The papers contain correspondence, manuscripts, book reviews, articles, lectures, off-prints, clippings, biographical material, radio broadcasts, tape recordings, a film, books, copies of the newsletter Bulletin, and pamphlets. Papers document Palyi's work as a conservative economist.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Melchior Palyi was born in Budapest, Hungary in 1892. He received his Doctorate in Economics from the University of Munich in 1915. From 1918 to 1933 Palyi taught at the University of Munich, the University of Goettingen and the University of Kiel. In 1927, he first came to the United States as a visiting professor at the University of Chicago. 1928 saw Palyi as an economist at the Deutsche Bank. Until 1931, Palyi was also a Professor of Finance at the Graduate School of Commerce in Berlin. For the next three years he held two posts important in the financial reconstruction of the German economy: he was the principal economic advisor to the Reichsbank and the Managing Director of the Institute for Currency Research, Berlin.
By 1933, Palyi had immigrated to the United States. He became a visiting professor and research economist at the University of Chicago and the University of Wisconsin. During the years 1943-1944, Palyi gave a series of radio talks on WIND, dealing with economic and social problems caused by the war in Europe. In 1945, he became a war correspondent and wrote articles for the Chicago Tribune and the Jackson Citizen Patriot newspapers. After the war, Palyi returned to Chicago and continued teaching and lecturing.
The 1950s saw Palyi producing such works as Compulsory Medical Care and the Welfare State (1950), The Dollar Dilemma: Perpetual Aid to Europe, and Managed Money at the Crossroads (1958). Palyi, as seen through his books and articles, represented the "conservative" faction of American economists during the middle of the 20th century.
In 1960, Melchior Palyi became a visiting professor and research economist at Northwestern University. From 1961 to 1968 Palyi wrote a weekly column for the Chicago Tribune entitled, "Comment," which dealt with various economic problems in the United States and the world as well as local problems. Also in 1961, Palyi produced a small but foresighted book that he entitled An Inflation Primer. This book attempted to get at the various causes for spiraling inflation and the accompanying recessionary periods. From 1962 to 1970, Palyi also wrote a regular column for the Chicago Commercial and Financial Chronicle which was entitled "Point of View."
Melchior Palyi, after 78 years of studying, advising, and teaching about world economics, died on July 29, 1970. In 1971 one of his greatest works was published posthumously. The Twilight of Gold dealt with a subject that fascinated Palyi all of his life: the gold standard. In this book he talks about the classical gold standard, the post-World War I monetary climate and its relationship to gold stabilization (which includes an interesting section entitled "Social Justice vs. Gold") and the New Gold Standard. "Prelude to Catastrophe" is a section which discusses flaws in the international credit structure and the American debt behemoth and the speculative euphoria. "Destabilization (1931-1936)" deals with the demise of the "Gold Bloc." The final section of the text proper deals with the demise of the gold standard. Additionally, there is a postscript entitled "Does History Repeat Itself?"
Scope Note
The Melchior Palyi papers have been arranged into five series. Series I includes biographical materials, awards, and honorary degrees. Series II contains correspondence arranged chronologically, including personal letters to Palyi and some copies of letters from him to other people. The majority of correspondence dates from 1931 to 1933. Series III contains writing by Palyi and others, including book reviews, articles, lectures and notes, as well as the WIND radio talks dealing with the war in Europe. Series IV contains The Bulletin, a privately circulated newsletter on economic and social issues. Series V includes newspaper clippings about Palyi, his minor books, and off-print copies of his articles.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/e/spcl/select.html
Subject Headings
Palyi, Melchior, 1892-1970; Economics; Economists
INVENTORY
- Series I: Biographical Materials
  - Biographical material, awards, honorary degrees, 1942-1968 and undated (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Correspondence, general, 1915-1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Deutsche Bundesbank, 1929-1933 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, general, 1930 - September 1931 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, general, October 1931 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, general, November 1931 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, general, December 1931 - May 1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, general, June - December 1932 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, general, 1933-1943 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - War correspondence, 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, general, 1945-1970 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series III: Manuscripts
  - Book reviews, 1943-1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Book reviews, Chicago Tribune, financial, 1948-1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Book reviews, miscellaneous and economic material, 1936-1965 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - WIND radio broadcasts, 1943 and Round Table, January 1 and March 26, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - WIND radio broadcasts, January - February 1944 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - WIND radio broadcasts, March - May 1944 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - WIND radio broadcasts, June - August 1944 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - WIND radio broadcasts, September - November 1944 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Writings, 1935, 1947, undated, "Study of the Financial Structures of the Chicago Area" "The American Students' Revolt Against Authority" "Divide and Rule" "From Regimentation to Corruption" "Term Loans" "Are We Going into Inflation?" "Five Year Plan and Russian Foreign Policy" "In Search of the Lost Monetary System" "Inflation Means Labor Trouble" "The Third Alternative" "The Bretton Woods Fallacy" " Pains and Depression-Anxieties" "February, 1947 - Comments" (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Writings, 1947-1948, undated, "The Prospect of Interest Rates and of the Bond Market" "Preamble" "Appeasements, Old and New" "Memorandum from Dr. Melchior Palyi" "July, 1947 - Comments" "The Steel Bottleneck" "Some Aspects of Military Conscription" "Some Reflections on Inflation" "Glancing at 1948: An Economic Letter" "October 1, 1948" "Europe's Frustration by Capital Flight" "Potential Exports from Germany" "How Long Will the War Last?" "Outsmarting Inflation" "Post-War Boom" "Inflation by Escalator" "Europe's Penal Colony" "What Happened to National Debts" (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Writings, 1944-1945, 1952, undated, "Anglo-American Competition" "The Sino-Russian `Deal'" "Hard Bargain, Harry Hopkins Style" "The New International Charter" "The Soviets ‘Reform’ Central Europe" "The Soviets Back to Normal" "What Makes the Stock Market Tick?" "Japanese Peace Prospect" "What of the European Balance of Power?" "Rubles Rolling Over Central Europe" "Post-War Cost Inflation" "What's Wrong With Italy?" "Soviet Bureaucratism vs. Nazi Feudalism" "To Be Or Not To Be - The Scapegoat" "Fresh Air in Washington" "Deflation in Belgium" "Back to Isolation?" "Freedom from Worry vs. Freedom from Fear" "Persian Oil and Balance of Power Politics" "American Elections and Post-War International Relations" "What About Estate Taxes?" "Freedom of Poland - Moscow Version" "Putting the (Tax) Cart Before the (Budget) Horse" "Burial at Dumbarton Oaks" "The Hard Treatment for Germany" "Peace Secured By Spending?" "The Balkan Jig-Saw Puzzle" "An Epitaph for Hitler" "From Vienna to Dumbarton Oaks" "The Simple Ways of International Double-Crossing" "Spreading the Financial Disease" "The Six Freedoms of the Bretton Woods Charter" "The Crisis in Naziland" "Post-War Depression?" "Is Stalin Going Conservative?" "The Economists of Monsieur DeGaulle" "Year-End Defeats" "Axis Morale" "The Soviet Blockade of China" "Stabilizing the World at Bretton Woods" "Russia Offers Appeasement" "Disenchanted Nationalizers" (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous and fragmented articles; "Point of View"; lists of Bulletin (includes titles and dates); Monetary Inflation, 1932-1936,1942-1947, 1963-1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
  - The Dollar: An Agonizing Reappraisal, manuscript copy, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - The Dollar: An Agonizing Reappraisal, 2 corrected copies (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - An Inflation Primer, final copy, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  - An Inflation Primer, notes and corrections, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - The Twilight [Eclipse] of Gold, original typescript, fragmentary, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - The Twilight [Eclipse] of Gold, typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - The Twilight [Eclipse] of Gold, typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 1-6)
  - The Twilight [Eclipse] of Gold, draft with corrections, sections I-II, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - The Twilight [Eclipse] of Gold, sections III-IV, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - The Twilight [Eclipse] of Gold, sections V and VII, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - The Twilight [Eclipse] of Gold, section VIII, A, B, C - IX, A, B, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - The Twilight [Eclipse] of Gold, Part I, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
  - The Twilight [Eclipse] of Gold, Part II, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - The Twilight [Eclipse] of Gold, Part II, undated (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Economic Systems, fragmentary, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Reviews of Palyi's books and related correspondence, 1935-1973, undated (Box 7, Folder 4-6)
  - Notes and materials on miscellaneous subjects, including lectures; French Stabilization, 1961-1962 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
  - Writings, 1934-1956, undated, "Bolshevism, Fascism and Hitlerism," undated "Do You Really Believe in Capitalism," 1956 "Contemporary Monetary Problems," 1940 "War Financing and Its Implications," 1943 "Some Outstanding European Economic Problems," lecture, February 15, 1934 "Some Outstanding European Problems: Industrial Economics of a Frozen Continent," lecture, February 28, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Discussions in Germany, 1932 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Addresses and Lectures, 1934, 1940-1941, 1951, undated, "The Aftermath of Inflation" "Canada's Supply of Money" "When Money Disappears" "The Philosophy of Pump Priming" "Defense Bonds vs. Inflation" "The Future of Interest Rates" "Prospects and `Economics' of the Presidential Election" "Are We Heading for Dictatorship?" "The Basis For Confidence" "On: Moody's Basis for Confidence" "The Economic Phases of the European Crisis" "Let Us Help England While We Arm" (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Addresses and Lectures, 1941, undated, "On the Prospects of War in the Far East" "The Prospects of a Long War" "Interest Rates in the Garrison State" "The Gold Lining of American Business" "If Hitler Wins" "The Reversed War Situation" "The Myth of Mr. Roosevelt's Humanitarianism" "America's Position in World Economy" (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Palyi, lectures on economics, 1938-1955, undated (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
  - Tables relating to gold, foreign market prices, etc., undated (Box 8, Folder 6-7)
  - Banks, wholesale price tables in U.S., France, Germany, England, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Research notes and tables relating to gold standard, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Spar-Bund, Germany, 1932-1933 (Box 8, Folder 10-11)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts, "Devaluation: Its Rationale, If Any," etc., 1941, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Principles of Mortgage Banking Regulation in Europe, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - The German Crisis, 1931-1937, 1967, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Lectures, rough drafts, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Lectures, notes on international finance, gold, debts, and Miscellaneous, 1929-1944, undated (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
  - Industrial concentration studies, 1961, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous notes on economics materials, etc., 1952, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous notes on economics materials, etc., 1930, 1934, 1967, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous published writings, 1916-1970, undated (Box 10, Folder 2-4)
  - Announcements of lectures, talks and seminars, 1940-1959, undated (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
  - Announcements of talks, lectures, and seminars, 1939-1964, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Announcements of talks, lectures, and seminars, 1934-1965 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - Chicago Journal of Commerce, January - May, 1942 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Commercial and Financial Chronicle, various editions, August 1943 - December 1953 (Box 11, Folder 4-7)
  - Commercial and Financial Chronicle, various editions, February 1954 - September 1966 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Offprints,1933-1970, undated, "Betrachtungen zur Konjunkturlage in den Vereinigten Staaten" "Zinssätze und Preise in den U.S.A." "What is Russia Waiting For?" "The Effects of the World Conflict on American Economy" "Technischer Fortschritt und Industrielle Konzentration" "Sind lähmende Streiks nicht zu vermeiden?" "Technischer Fortschritt und industrielle Konzentration" "Kostensenkung und industrielle Konzentration" "Kann die amerikanische Rezession kontrolliert werden?" "Der herrlichen sechziger Jahre" "Konjunkturrückgang oder abschwächung in den Vereinigten Staaten?" "Gedanken zur Rezession in den Vereinigten Staaten" "Canute at the Treasury" "The French Monetary Situation" "Wie steht es um den Dollar?" "Konzentration und monoplistische Macht" "Fortschritt contra Konzentration" "Deutsches kapital für Vereinigten Staaten?" "Europe Turning Again to Gold Standard?" "New Economics' Singular Feat: A Tower of Debt" "New Britain" "Economic Perspectives," series of 7 articles "An ABC of Inflation" "Some Aspects of Governmental Debts" (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Offprints, 1938-1964, undated, "Volkswirtschaftlicher Rock and Roll" "Interest Rates and the Defense Program" "Good as a Dollar - How Good is It?" "Die Wirtschaftsorganisation Sowjetrublands und sein Aussenhandel" "Was I Surprised!" "Betrachtungen zur amerikanischen Konjunkturlage" "How Sick is State Medicine?" "Results of 25 Years of the Great American Inflation" "The Introduction of Adam Smith on the Continent" "Virulent Inflation and Investment Experience" "The Liquidation of an Induced Prosperity," [The Pyramid of Sigma Tau, p. 8] "Bank Portfolios and the Control of the Capital Market" "Real Estate and Realities on the International Scene" "Present Federal Reserve Policies" "Open-Market Policy and Totalitarian Control" "Zehn Jahre erfahrungen mit Verstaatlichungen VII)" "Basic Factors in International Competition" (Box 12, Folder 3-4)
  - "Point of View," September 1965 - December 1966 (Box 12, Folder 5-6)
  - "Point of View," 1967 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - "Point of View," 1968 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - "Point of View," 1969 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - A Point of View (1970) (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Articles, 1933-1961 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Press Clippings, prediction of Allied victory, World War II, 1942 (Box 13, Folder 3-4)
  - Articles about Palyi, 1927-1937 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Articles about Palyi, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Articles about Palyi, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Articles about Palyi, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Articles about Palyi, 1941 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Articles about Palyi, 1942 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Articles about Palyi, 1943 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Articles about Palyi, 1944-1946 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Articles about Palyi, 1951-1959 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Articles about Palyi, 1960-1970 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Articles about Palyi, undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Max Weber, "The Theory of Social and Economic Organization," undated (Box 14, Folder 8-10)
  - Maurice Allais, "Quelques donnees relative: a la reforme du systeme monetaire international," 1930, 1945, undated (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
  - Twilight of Gold, final proofs with introduction by Professor Klemmer, 1972 (Box 15, Folder 3-5)
- Series IV: The Bulletin
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 1-8, February - June 1941 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 9-18, July - December 1941 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 19-28, January - June 1942 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 29-31, July - August 1942 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, January 8, 1943 letter; nos. 38-48, September 1942 - June 1943 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 49-58, July - December 1943 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 59-69, January - June 1944 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 70-78, July - December 1944 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 79-88, January - June 1945 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 89-99, July - December 1945 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 100-111, January - June 1946 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 112-120, July - December 1946 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 121-132, January - June 1947 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 133-143, July - December 1947 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 144-154, January - June 1948 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 155-165, July - December 1948 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 166-174, January - June 1949 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 175-183, July - December 1949 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 184-194, January - June 1950 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 195-208, July - December 1950 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 209-221, January - June 1951 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 222-230, July - December 1951 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 231-240, January - June 1952 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 241-251, July - December 1952 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 252-262, January - June 1953 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 263-273, July - December 1953 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 274-284, January - June 1954 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 285-293, July - December 1954 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 294-303, January - June 1955 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 304-309, July - December 1955 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 310-319, January - June 1956 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 320-331, July - December 1956 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 332-342, January - June 1957 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 343-352, July - December 1957 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 353-363, January - June 1958 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 364-372, July - December 1958 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 373-385, January - June 1959 and February 12, 1959 speech (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 386-397, July - December 1959 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 398-408, January - June 1960 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - M. Palyi, Bulletin, nos. 409-415, July - December 1960 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - M. Palyi, The Bulletin, nos. 416-431, January - June 1961 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - M. Palyi, The Bulletin, nos. 432-442, July - December 1961 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - M. Palyi, The Bulletin, nos. 443-454, January - June 1962 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - M. Palyi, The Bulletin, nos. 455-467, July - December 1962 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - M. Palyi, The Bulletin, nos. 468-480, January - June 1963 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - M. Palyi, The Bulletin, nos. 481-490, July - December 1963 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - M. Palyi, The Bulletin, nos. 491-501, January - June 1964 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - M. Palyi, The Bulletin, nos. 502-511, July - December 1964 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - M. Palyi, The Bulletin, nos. 512-524, January - June 1965 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - M. Palyi, The Bulletin, nos. 525-535, July - December 1965 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - M. Palyi, The Bulletin, nos. 536-544, January - June 1966 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - M. Palyi, The Bulletin, nos. 545-555, July - December 1966 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - M. Palyi, The Bulletin, nos. 556-564, January - June 1967 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - M. Palyi, The Bulletin, nos. 565-576, July - December 1967 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - M. Palyi, The Bulletin, nos. 577-587, January - June 1968 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - M. Palyi, The Bulletin, nos. 588-591, 594-597, 599, July - June 1969 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - M. Palyi, The Bulletin, nos. 615-624, July - 1970 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Tape recording, "Freedom and Monetary Policy," March 6, 1963, University of Illinois (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Film, "The Dollar: An Agonizing Reappraisal," 1966 (Box 22, Folder 1)
- Series V: Books and Pamphlets
  - Subseries 1: German-language Books and Articles
    - Mutliple volumes of Pitaval, 1904-1909 (Box 22, Folder 2-4)
    - Multiple volumes of Der Pitaval der Gegenwart, 1910-1911 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Articles, Copy of Die Kreditlage der Deutschen Landwirtschaft im Wirtschaftsjahr 1931/32, 1933 Copy of festschrift for Hans Mayer, 1949 Copy of Archiv fuer Rechts- und Sozialphilosophie, 1957 Two copies of Ordo: Jahrbuch fuer die Ordnung von Wirtschaft und Gesellschaft, 1958, 1967 Copy of Kyklos: Internationale Zeitschrift fuer Sozialwissenschaften, 1960 Copy of Gedenkschrift zur Verleihung des Freiherr-Vom-Stein-Preises 1960, 1960 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Articles, Copies of Franz Boehm, Wilhelm Grewe, Walther Hoffmann, and Constantino Bresciani-Turroni," 1931 and "Kapitalmangel und Waehrungsstabilisierung," 1949 Friedrich Burgdoerfer. Voelker am Abgrund, 1936 Franz Eulenburg, "Europaeische Handelspolitik," 1935 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Articles, Heinrich Gieveking, "Die Hamburger Bank, 1619-1875," undated Walter Grau, "Zur Vereinheitlichung der Vorbild fuer Justiz und Verwaltung," undated Oswald Hahn, "Die Auswirkungen der bargeldlosen Einkommenszahlung auf die Waerungsstabilitaet," 1960 Wilhelm Hasenack. Wirtschaftsgefahren an der Ruhr durch Demontagen, 1948 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Articles, Ferdinand A. Hermens. Ethik, Politik und Macht, 1961 Rudolph Kaulla. Beitraege zur Entstehungsgeschichte des Geldes, 1945 Rudolf Meimberg. Alternativen der Ordnung, 1956 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Articles, Wilhelm Muscheidt, "Unterbewertung und Ueberbewertung des Franc," 1947 Fritz Neumark, "Ausgleichsprobleme der oeffentlichen Finanzwirtschaft," 1937 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Several writings of Max Planck, 1938-1941 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Articles, Kurt Ritter, "Zu Einigen Aktuellen Tendendzen und Widerspruechen in der Kapitalistischen Landwirtschaft," 1958 Wilhelm Roepke, "Gegenhaltung und Gegengesinnung der Freien Welt," 1955 Alexander Ruestow, "Die Zukunft des Unternehmertums," 1956 Alexander Ruestow, "Die weltgeschichtliche Bedeutung des Bauerntums in Vergangenheit, Gegenwart und Zukunft," undated Lajos Schmidt, "Die Loehne der landwirtschaftlichen Arbeiter in Ungarn," 1943 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Articles, Guenter Schmoelders, "Von der "Quantitaetstheorie" zur "Liquiditaetstheorie" des Geldes," 1960 Felix Somary. Die Ursachen der Krise, 1932 Friedrich Stieve. Ubriss der Deutschen Geschichte von 1792 bis 1933, 1936 A. Teleki, "Wirtschaft im Krieg," 1941 Wilhelm Vocke, "Aspekte der internationalen Waehrungsprobleme nach der Konferenz von Tokio, Herbst 1964" (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 2: French-language Books and Articles